Daniel Souza

danieliscoding@gmail.com

+44 07796796655

linkedin.com/in/danielsouza

http://danielsouza.org

Summary

Experienced Product Designer, specialist in Information Architecture and User Research. Daniel has spent the last 20 years designing services, systems and experiences for complex software while empowering product and creative teams to deliver user-centred products and services.

With experience in start-ups, scale-ups and corporations, Daniel is a design leader who unlocks collaboration in multidisciplinary and distributed teams.

Experience



Head of Design

BT Group

Apr 2023 - Nov 2023 (8 months)

- Partner with product leads and engineers to ship the company EE ID Identity Services, a platform that supports millions of users across three brands - a business-critical feature (SSO, Account Creation)
- Led the multidisciplinary team for the Identity Tribe (Product Designers, Content Designers, Service Designers, Researchers, and Accessibility Specialists)
- Hiring and building a team of designers, researchers and content designers for the Co-create tribe (mobile and retail transformation)

F Senior Design Manager - Operations and Design Systems

FARFETCH

Jun 2021 - Apr 2023 (1 year 11 months)

- Contributed to key features to improve the company b2c e-commerce operations, with customers across 150+ countries
- Led 5 (five) Principal Designers in evolving and maintaining the Design System, libraries (React) and documentation standards for IOS/Android
- Led product strategy sessions, road mapping and end-to-end execution of cross-team bets with reviews from C-level executives and senior product directors
- Worked with Devs, Accessibility team and QA's for quality assurance and implementation of experience metrics (System Usability Score) and WCAG compliance
- Led the implementation of the development framework for Product Designers (+50)
- Facilitated the creation of a skill matrix with 10+ designers and managers across all tribes
- Responsible for the Workshop Facilitation, Service Prototyping and Content Design Practices

Senior Design Manager

eMed Healthcare UK

Apr 2019 - Apr 2021 (2 years 1 month)

- Hired to support Chief Design Officer, Research and Design Directors
- Partnered with Director of Product and engineering Leads to establish a design system and accessibility practice to support new markets

- Established Async Collaboration practices to support offices in Austin, London and APAC locations
- Led series of workshops with C-level execs, Clinical Directors, User Researchers and Design teams to create a new vision for clinical services, supporting the company expansion in the US. This work was focused on improving usability for users with low literacy and disabilities with the adoption of component libraries in the codebase We delivered a new app used by thousands of patients in the US.

Associate Creative Director, Experience Design

Publicis Sapient

Oct 2016 - Apr 2019 (2 years 7 months)

- As a consultant, I've led Design and Research in Lloyds Digital Transformation Program (Commercial Banking workstream)
- Designed 0-1 experience for complex transactional use cases (internet banking) as part of the agile team triad (Product, Engineering, Design)
- Led work to design and deploy machine learning-based experiences to support investment banking and mortgages decision processes
- Led the adoption of the company design system into Commercial Banking
- Was part of the Global Design Leadership at Sapient, responsible for studio events, learning experiences and improving hiring practices (DEI champion)
- Established Conversation Design as a discipline, training +30 designers and content writers, contributing to projects for HSBC, Unilever and BA.

IXDA Local Leader - Brasília

IxDA

Jul 2014 - Sep 2016 (2 years 3 months)

- Established the city chapter, collaborating with IXDA leaders across the country
- Represented Brasil in the IXDA conference in San Francisco
- Co-created seminars, workshops and educational curriculum to support new UX practitioners.

Associate Creative Director - User Experience Design

Isobar

Apr 2014 - Sep 2016 (2 years 6 months)

- Led multidisciplinar teams working for Banco do Brasil digital transformation
- Established Content Strategy as a practice
- Grew the team from 4 to 16 professionals, establishing learning goals, career development plans and training.

m User Experience Consultant

Moringa

May 2013 - Apr 2014 (1 year)

Senior Interaction Designer

Try Consultoria

Oct 2012 - Apr 2013 (7 months)

- Leading streams of work for financial services, mainly on improving usability and accessibility for Internet Banking applications

Planner, User Experience

Aug 2012 - Oct 2012 (3 months)



Planning Manager

Wunderman

Aug 2011 - Aug 2012 (1 year 1 month)

Led a cross-functional group of talented writers, designers, planners and analysts in order to deliver digital campaigns, social media strategies and mobile applications for Vivo, the leader mobile operator in Brazil.

As one of the heads of the account, my role required constant communication and negotiation with IT, Project, Creative and Account teams and close relationship with senior client stakeholders.

Analytics & Research Coordinator

Mar 2010 - Aug 2011 (1 year 6 months)

Created the Research and Analytics practice. Hired and trained a team of six awesome analysts to dig, crunch and transform user behavior, conversation and activity data into insights and easy to digest information.

Senior User Experience Architect

Jan 2009 - Mar 2010 (1 year 3 months)

Worked as a principal e-Government Strategist

Senior Information Architect

Knowtec

Sep 2007 - Dec 2008 (1 year 4 months)

Planned, Designed and managed projects for NGO's, Financial companies and Brands. I had the opportunity to create the first Online Volunteering website in Brazil, from conception to launch.



Information Architect

Isobar

Jan 2007 - Sep 2007 (9 months)

Information Architect and Interaction Designer.

E-commerce Manager

Insinuante

Dec 2003 - May 2005 (1 year 6 months)

Business development, strategic planning, information architecture and technology management. When the project was finished, i had the opportunity to manage a team with Customer Service, Development, Designers, Marketing and Sales (about 20 people) in order to startup the e-commerce operation. Today, it's one of the biggest online retailers in Brazil.

Education



Centro Universitário UNA

Database Administration

Cefet

Technical, Eletromechanics

Licenses & Certifications



UX Design Techniques: Ideation - Lynda.com

Issued Oct 2016 - Expires Oct 2016 F281EA



CSPO - Scrum Alliance

Issued Dec 2018 - Expires Dec 2020 865463

lw Service Design - Livework São Paulo

Skills

Information Architecture • User Experience • Requirements Gathering • Creative Concept Development • User Interface Design • Web Analytics • Information Design • Product Design • Service Design • UX Research